原视频名：Why The Engines That Flew On Saturn V Rocket Look Different In Museums
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/HkObNfCki6M
原视频发布日期：20190307
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And I've been really happy with the last week
上周我一直很高兴
hearing the number of people that wholeheartedly agree with my recommendation to watch this Apollo 11 documentary
因为听说有些人完全同意我对这部阿波罗11号纪录片的推荐
which is currently in IMAX for a very limited engagement
而目前这部纪录片正在IMAX进行非常有限的上映
and they're not paying me to say this.
而且他们也没有让我恰饭
I think this is a magnificent piece of work.
我认为这是一个壮丽的作品
But why I found interesting is
但我发现有趣的是
the number of people that have come to me with questions of things that they have seen for the first time
有些人会问我一些他们第一次发现的问题
so I want to talk about one very specific thing that people have asked me about.
那么我想说说人们问我的一件非常具体的事情
During the launch sequence, we get to see underneath the back end of a Saturn V powered by its 5 F1 engines
在发射过程中 我们可以看到土星五号的下部 由五台F1发动机提供动力
the most powerful single chambered engines that have ever flown.
F1是有史以来最强大的单室发动机
And you've probably seen a few still photos showing
而你可能已经看过一些静态的照片
the massive size of these engines with an industry-standard Wernher von Braun for scale
这些照片展示了发动机的巨大尺寸与行业标准 的冯·布劳恩进行了对比
but despite being massive they are also intricately detailed
尽管F1发动机巨大无比 但同时也是精细而复杂的
with lots of piping throughout the chamber walls
燃烧室内壁上有很多管道
to protect the engine from the massive amount of heat that it generates.
以保护发动机不受其产生的大量热量的影响
But the engines we see propelling Apollo 11 upwards
但我们看到的推动阿波罗11号上升的发动机是
look like they're made of hammered sheet metal.
看起来就像用锤子敲打的金属板做的
There are several examples of F1 engines on display in museums and other places
在博物馆和其他一些地方 展出的几个F1发动机的样品
and they all show the the detailed version.
都是有细节的版本
They don't show this rough version.
而不是这个粗糙的版本
When you see the Saturn V which is on display the fully assembled version
当你看到完全组装的土星五号时
the engines do not look like the engines we see on the Apollo 11 Saturn V.
其发动机看起来也不像我们在阿波罗11号的土星5号上看到的发动机
So what's going on here is
那么这里发生的事情是
that the engines were covered with an inconel file with an asbestos insulation layer
发动机上覆盖着带有石棉隔热层的铬镍铁合金
because they want to protect the engines from extra heat.
因为他们想保护发动机不受额外热量的影响
During testing they began to get worried about the heat radiating out from other engines.
在测试过程中 他们开始担心其他发动机散发出来的热量
In particular that core engine was going to be experiencing a lot more heat than the outside engines.
尤其是那台中央发动机要比外面的发动机经受更多的热量
But also as the rocket got higher and faster
但同时 随着火箭越飞越高 越飞越快
a combination of the lowering air pressure and the aerodynamic effects
在气压降低和气动力的混合效应作用之下
would actually start to pool the rocket exhaust up back in towards the engines
实际上 火箭的废气会开始向发动机方向汇集
and indeed up the side of the rocket.
而实际上这是发生在火箭的侧面
What happens is the tip of the rocket is hitting into the air and it creates a shock cordon point
这是因为火箭的尖端刺入空气 形成了激波
where the air is basically being accelerated and behind that shock cordon the air pressure becomes much lower.
空气在激波上被加速 而在激波面后面 气压变得更低
Because it's much lower, it's actually sucking the rocket exhaust back up
因为气压低得多 所以这片区域实际上是把火箭的废气吸回来了
and it starts to rise up the side of the rocket.
然后废气开始上升到火箭的一侧
It's really fascinating to watch this with something like the Saturn V where they have these great tracking shots.
在土星五号这样的火箭上看到这样的画面真的很迷人 因为跟拍镜头很不错
But it doesn't just happen with a Saturn V.
但这不仅仅是发生在土星五号上
It happens with a lot of different rockets.
在很多不同的火箭都会出现这种情况
Here it is under Space Shuttle
这是在航天飞机下面
where the low-pressure area behind the external tank starts to suck exhaust gasses in there.
外置储罐下面的低压区开始将废气吸入其中
And the bottom of that ends up getting burnt quite severely during the launch.
而在发射过程中 储罐底部最终被烧得相当严重
It's amazing to think the Space Shuttle is moving supersonic at this point
令人惊讶的是 航天飞机此时正在以超音速飞行
but the entrained atmosphere and gases around the structure is actually pulling exhaust gasses forwards.
但结构周围夹带的气体实际把废气往前拉动了
So you can imagine
所以你可能会想
why the designers might have decided to add this extra thermal protection at some point in the process.
为什么设计者会在某个阶段决定添加这种额外的热保护措施
The reason why we don't see this on most of the engines and museums is
为什么我们在大多数博物馆的发动机中没有看到这个的原因在于
because the insulation wasn't added by the engine manufacturers
隔热层不是由发动机制造商添加的
and it wasn't added when the stage was assembled.
而且它不是在分级组装阶段时添加的
It was added in the Vehicle Assembly Building when they were stacking the rocket.
它是在火箭组装大楼里堆叠火箭时才加进去的
And apparently it took something like 800 to a thousand man-hours of work to put this on there.
而很明显 花了800到1000个工时才完成了安装
The actual design of the thermal protection system is pretty simple.
热保护系统的设计实际上非常简单
It's a pair of layers of inconel foil separated by an asbestos insulating layer.
在两片铬镍铁合金金属箔中间 夹着石棉绝缘层
And yeah look you can see the engine wrapped up in this in the Apollo 4 launch.
是的 在阿波罗4号的发射中 就可以看到发动机被包裹在里面
That was a very first Saturn V launch.
那是土星五号的第一次发射
I think this is a great shot
我觉得这个镜头很好
because you can also see the film cooling layer where it transitions then to the actual proper exhaust.
因为你也可以看到气膜冷却层 在此之后 低温富燃废气转变成正常的废气
I think the reason why many people haven't seen this is
我想很多人没有注意到这个细节的原因是
because well first of all the launches are very spectacular
因为首先 发射是非常壮观的
so actually noticing that detail that difference in the engines is a tall order
所以 其实注意到这个发动机差别的细节是一个很高的要求
when you've got this ridiculously bright contrast.
而且这时的对比度也非常高
But equally the images that we have from the early testing
但同样的 我们从早期测试中得到的图像也是如此
they show the engines being tested without this
他们展示了没有使用这种隔热措施而进行测试的发动机
and also there was no cameras placed underneath the spacecraft when it was sitting on the launch pad
而且 当火箭放在发射台上时 也没有在其下方放置相机
so we get didn't get to see the images of that generally.
所以总的来说 我们没能看到那种的画面
The first time I found out about them is
我第一次发现这个细节是在
when I got given this book the NASA Saturn V Owners' Workshop Manual.
我拿到这本NASA土星五号车主车间手册 的时候
I don't know. If you're in Britain you probably know the Haynes manuals from trying to fix your car.
我不清楚(你知道不) 如果你在英国 在试着修你的车的时候就可能知道海恩斯手册
They would tear down in a car and tell you how to fix things.
手册里会拆开一辆车 告诉你如何修理各种部件
I remember using one to replace the gear box on a Fiat Uno.
我记得我使用其中一本的知识 替换了菲亚特乌诺的齿轮箱
That was fun.
这挺有趣的
But more recently they seem to be doing a pretty good business
但最近 他们似乎做了一个相当不错的生意
creating manuals for things like the Saturn V the Space Shuttle and the Starship Enterprise.
为土星五号 航天飞机和星舰企业号制作了手册
But the Saturn V and the Apollo missions are just such big complicated things.
但土星五号和阿波罗任务都太大太复杂了
There are so many tiny pieces of minutia that you will learn
你会了解到这么多细枝末梢的东西 可以去学
and it's fun. It's great.
针不戳
I mean the only don't say it is that sometimes say you make a blockbuster movie like Apollo 13
我是指 有人没提到 那个轰动一时的阿波罗13号 电影
and then realize afterwards that actually the engines are wrong.
却用错了发动机
It's still a great movie.
不过 这仍然是一部伟大的电影
And before you ask, first man got it correct.
在你问之前 已经有人指出了错误
But while the special effects are cool and all that
尽管特效之类的很酷
I think the real thing is where my heart is at.
但真正的问题是我所关心的东西
It is definitely the biggest practical effect
这绝对是最大的实际效果
and looking at the flames moving around here
而看着这里的火光四射
you can see why they might need to mod to retrofit some extra thermal protection on their engine.
你就可以理解为什么他们需要改装 需要在发动机上加装一些额外的热保护装置
And so that explains
这就解释了
why the engines on the Saturn Vs that actually launched all had this extra foil thermal protection over it
为什么实际发射的土星五号的发动机上都覆盖有额外的金属箔制做的热保护装置
which somehow never made it into the the museum versions or onto the examples that we see elsewhere on display.
而在某些原因的影响之下 博物馆或者其他地方展示中的发动机从来没有加上这些
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]